Jim Rollenhagen

Software Developer

616.617.9163 jim@jimrollenhagen.com https://jimrollenhagen.com

CAREER PROFILE

I am a software developer that enjoys designing, building, and operating large-scale software systems. I've primarily worked in Python, but am happy working in all sorts of tech stacks. I'm not afraid of the frontend, but backend development is where my skills truly shine.

When I'm not writing code, I am an enabler in every sense of the word, acting as a force multiplier for the people around me. I tear through political blockers, and anything else in the way, to allow people around me to solve real problems.

EXPERIENCE

Rackspace Hosting - Software Developer

2013 - 2017

- Worked primarily upstream on OpenStack Ironic as Project Team Lead and core reviewer.
- Served as Tech Lead for the Ironic project within the OpenStack Innovation Center, leading planning efforts and guiding other team members.
- Built and operated OnMetal, a bare metal public cloud.
- Planned, architected, built, and operated OnMetal v2, a major improvement on OnMetal.
- Implemented zero-downtime upgrades for the OnMetal products, allowing our team to go from monthly deploys to multiple deploys per week.
- Mentored teammates to help them grow as engineers.
- Jumped in to help other teams with technical problems when needed.

OpenStack Ironic - Project Team Lead and Core Reviewer

2014 - Present

- Served as Project Team Lead (PTL) for Mitaka, Newton, and Ocata development cycles. Set roadmap and priorities. Team increased commit frequency by 20% from Mitaka to Newton, and 60% from Newton to Ocata.
- Served as core reviewer, approving code since summer 2014.
- Managed code releases since Liberty cycle, and changed release model from "every 6 months" to "when there's good code to release", typically 1-2 months.

- Led architecture of multi-tenant networking features, giving users private networking capabilities and integration with software networking systems.
- Led development and integration for the "agent" deploy driver, offering a more scalable and less error-prone deployment method.
- Developed high availability capabilities for the Ironic driver running in the nova-compute service.
- Worked with the Nova team to improve how scheduling works for Ironic instances.
- Repaired broken relationships with the Nova project team, leading to better collaboration between the teams.

ZeroCater - Software Engineer

2013

- Full-stack web development.
- Django, Postgres, Angular, AWS.
- Led planning of a new menu system to enable meal planners to more easily select the right meal for clients, and enable vendor management to more easily modify menus.
- Re-wrote the scheduling application from scratch to improve account manager efficiency.
- Built a number of small features to help our account managers make sure their clients were happily fed.

drchrono - Software Engineer

2013

- Full-stack web development.
- Django, JQuery, MySQL, Rackspace Cloud.
- Completely re-wrote the medical billing system, fixing how we interact with insurance companies and making sure doctors got paid.
- Wrote a certified electronic prescription service, allowing doctors to directly submit a patient's prescriptions to their preferred pharmacy, reducing errors and fake prescriptions.

General Motors - Software Engineer

2011 - 2012

- Built software to improve workflow and efficiency in the hybrid battery systems lab test engineering group.
- Wrote a JSON API frontend for the lab's monitoring software with periodic polling and caching of data. This allowed developers to avoid using an XSLT-based API that often took minutes to load.
- Built a responsive web interface to allow mobile users to monitor the lab as a whole, individual tests, and active alarms.
- Moved the test software team from using copies of source code with dates to mercurial.

- Wrote deployment tooling to safely distribute updated test scripts to test machines, and restart when the system was idle.
- Helped online new battery labs in Canada and China. Integrated new labs into central monitoring and deploy software, and assisted remote engineers with setup and problems.

General Motors - Software Engineer Co-op Student

2009 - 2011

- Built life-cycle test scripts for the first-generation Chevy Volt battery. A two
 year test simulates 10 years of driving. Enabled the test to be easily restarted
 to provide for software updates.
- Wrote software to pull data from Volt life-cycle test machines, aggregate the
 data, and build visualizations. This helped highlight anomalies and issues
 early, while giving management a 10,000 foot view of the progress and results.
- Contributed features and bug fixes to common test script code, including hardware device controllers and generic test blocks.
- Began effort to refactor code from test scripts for various battery models into common code.
- Made a prototype Android app to monitor and control basic functionality for test machines.

EDUCATION

Kettering University - BS in Computer Engineering

2005 - 2011

Minor in Computer Science

PROJECTS

My open source work is primarily around OpenStack, in a few different projects.

- Ironic Ironic's mission is to produce an OpenStack service and associated libraries capable of managing and provisioning physical machines, and to do this in a security-aware and fault-tolerant manner.
 https://github.com/openstack/ironic
- Nova Nova's mission is to implement services and associated libraries to provide massively scalable, on demand, self service access to compute resources, including bare metal, virtual machines, and containers. https://github.com/openstack/nova